[Music]
hello and welcome everyone it's active
lab live stream number
38.0 february 10th 2022.
we're going to be discussing the paper
the evolution of brain architectures for
predictive coding and active inference
welcome to the active inference lab we
are a participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at some of the links here on the slide
this is recorded in an archive live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve on our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we'll be following good
video etiquette for live streams it's
going to be a solo stream though
go to activeinference.org if you want to
learn more about how to participate or
contribute or get involved with any
actinflab project and check out this
coda link to see past and upcoming live
streams
the page looks like this so you can see
events that haven't happened yet like 39
40.
and then also you can look back and you
can see who is participating and read
the papers and all of that
so
check it out
today in active stream
number 38 the goal is to learn and
discuss this cool paper the evolution of
brain architectures for predictive
coding and active inference
the papers by giovanni pizzulo thomas
parr and carl firsten from december 2021
and just like all videos
it's just an introduction to some of the
ideas it's not a review or a final word
so go check out the paper to learn more
and there's going to be an overview with
first names and claims abstract and
roadmap
all right i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
the big question that this paper is
getting at is
what is the evolutionary
neurophysiological basis of cognition
and how do complex cognitive phenotypes
arise
so how do things
develop and evolve
how they think and how does that change
over evolutionary time
and shown here are three images
representing three scales of analysis of
looking at ant cognition so on the left
is a representation of the synapse with
the glia wrapped around it and the
molecules and some of the mechanisms
because changes in those mechanisms can
influence cognition
then in the middle is a 3d
representation of an amp brain with the
different brain regions like the central
complex and the
optic and the olfactory lobes
and this represents the level of
regional or
micro or
mesoanatomical variation and that
definitely changes over evolutionary
time just like the synaptic level
and then there's this behavioral
ecological level and that's where the
ants are engaging in collective behavior
and stigmargy and so
how's this how does this all work
how does this all work in today's ants
and how has it evolved and then expand
that to other species and other
questions
the paper was published right at the end
of 2021 in december
in
the
royal society of publishing
and just to go over the aims and claims
of the paper
this is in the author's words
there's growing consensus that the
brains of humans and other
phylogenetically derived or advanced
organisms operate in a predictive manner
across perception
predictive coding and action control
active inference
yet the ways in which our advanced
predictive abilities may have arisen
during evolution remain unclear
the goal of this article is to sketch an
evolutionary history of brain
architectures for predictive processing
a central tenet of our proposal is that
although prediction is often
characterized as a complex cognitive
function it is not a late evolutionary
addition of advanced animals like us
rather
in distinction to a late-stage cognitive
argument like saying language is what
makes us an advanced cognizer
or semantic language with
certain types of syntax rather our
complex predictive abilities eg planning
and imagination
emerged gradually e.g via phyletic
gradualism
smooth changes through evolutionary time
or punctuated equilibrium
sharp changes through evolutionary time
but
punctuated at one scale is smooth at
another from simpler predictive and
error correction loops
eg motor and autonomic reflexes
that were already part of the brains of
our earlier evolutionary ancestors and
were key to solving adaptive regulation
problems
so just like
mike levin's paper was addressing the
question of basal cognition from the
bioelectric perspective here is going to
be more of a predictive processing and
action inference perspective on the
functional aspects not on the
mechanistic so the bioelectric was down
here at the level of cells
this is going to be approaching it from
a little bit of a different perspective
but we'll find out
here's the abstract
this article considers the evolution of
brain architectures for predictive
processing we argue that brain
mechanisms for predictive
perception and action are not late
evolutionary editions of advanced
creatures like us
rather they emerge gradually from
simpler predictive loops for example
autonomic and motor reflexes that were a
legacy from our earlier
evolutionary ancestors
and were key to solving their
fundamental problems of adaptive
regulation
we characterize simpler to more complex
brains formally in terms of generative
models that include predictive loops of
increasing hierarchical breadth and
depth
these may start from a simple
homeostatic motif and be elaborated
during evolution in four main ways these
include the multimodal expansion of
predictive control into an allostatic
loop
its duplication to form multiple sensory
motor loops that expand an animal's
behavioral repertoire
and the gradual endowment of general
generative models
with hierarchical depth to deal with
aspects of the world that unfold at
different spatial scales and temporal
depth to select which plans
select plans in a future oriented manner
in turn these elaborations underwrite
the solution to biological regulation
problems faced by increasingly
sophisticated animals
our proposal aligns neuroscientific
theorizing about predictive processing
with evolutionary and comparative data
on brain architectures in different
animal species and just looking ahead
here's a figure that we're going to get
to
here's the ancestral state it has this
structure it's a model
and then it's going to undergo a set of
different types of discrete operations
that change it structurally and that's
structure learning and it's going to
happen over evolutionary time scale and
it's going to be tied to functional
architectures for predictive processing
okay how do they go from here to there
this is the roadmap
after the introduction they introduce
predictive regulation and control
perception cognition and control action
as basic design principles of the brain
so kind of taking that embodied approach
but making it very operational and
functional so that it can be studied
from an evolutionary function
perspective
introducing the brain
as doing structure learning in
generative models over evolutionary and
also other time skills
they then give three examples of
simple predictive motifs in ancestral
brains which is the homeostatic control
the allostatic control and the simple
simple behavioral learning
then they introduce that figure that we
just looked at and that's the
evolutionary algebra of structure
learning just like you can multiply and
add these are kind of like operations on
evolutionary spaces
they then discuss a few finer points
related to behavioral switching temporal
depth hierarchical depth and then take a
phylogenetic perspective at the end
giving an example and there's a
discussion
okay
so
to go into section two and just sort of
deal with the keywords and themes as
they
are needed
here's figure one
uh in figure one the reason why we can
even jump in here without going to any
keywords is
it's
biology we're talking about and we can
jump in why not as good of a place as
any to go in at the action perception
loop and then connect it to some of the
analytical or mathematical formalisms of
active inference and the free energy
principle so this is figure one in the
paper in section two
the action perception cycle and
predictive regulation
so here's our entity our agent on the
left
and here is our world state on the right
the entity is engaged in prediction
while they're making observations that
are being emitted from the world that's
resulting in some discrepancy either
things are exactly as expected or not so
an example would be in the visual field
the brain is generating a prediction of
what is in the blind spot of the retina
and then if the eyes were to move there
to use action
changing the world in terms of the
stimuli coming in
through ocular motor action
that would result in a different
perception that could either confirm or
deny confirm
with a low discrepancy or
be very surprising with a high
discrepancy
what was expected about what was in the
blind spot which would confirm accuracy
in a visual model
so
in this partitioning of action and
perception which is just very
descriptive it's not quite the bayesian
graph that we're going to get to later
it's kind of like a flow model and
there's probably other flow models that
could be used as well but it turns out
that this partitioning or this way of
thinking about flow at least
conceptually
leads to in the active inference
proposal
this
idea of using
a free energy minimizing function over
some math that will get to a little bit
more formally in the next figure and
using a kind of combined metric that has
two parts the red and the blue
to make
decisions about
perception as well as action because it
turns out that perception and action and
cognition and metacognition are all part
of the entities model that it's doing
inference on in certain cases
so just to kind of throw back to
not so long ago
here we have the f
of q
that's the distribution that's under the
entity's control and y and so it's as a
function of beliefs and data there's
going to be some term
and so just looking back to 37
we looked at the variational free energy
and how that relates to perceptual
inference
where
there's a penalty for overfitting
as well as a penalty for failing to
explain the data so it's kind of making
a visual model
or a perceptual model that in that
snapshot given the priors and precision
and all of that
is not overfitting but it is fitting the
data and it's kind of existing on that
frontier and then it's using variational
inference to solve that in a really
tractable way
and then when action comes into play a
few things happen first the agent has to
incorporate their own preferences
because why care about action if you
don't even care why it's going to happen
so they have to incorporate their
preferences which is a non non-arbitrary
in a sense for action selection but it's
arbitrary in a higher level
as well as incorporating the fact that
there's uncertainty over the
consequences of action or just future
states of the world not just like sensor
measurement as in other cases so we have
to take this variational free energy
calculation that was just like snapshot
perception and expand it a little bit to
the expected free energy so here's f in
the background and now there's this
expected free energy term g
which is over
also an action selection policy z
and now there's kind of similar like
resonating or rhyming terms
but rather than over fitting
the imperative on the left side is to
satisfy preferences
on the right side the penalty for
failing to explain the data
is kind of transposed into this failing
to surprise or failing to minimize
expected surprise of future data so this
is like fitting the expectations well on
the right side in blue and then living
up to your preferences and expectations
in an optimistic way on the left so it's
kind of like realism on the right and
optimism on the left
and
that is what we talked about in 37 and
that's the partitioning that's being
done basically here
the authors are setting that up as the
action perception cycle and predictive
regulation just wanted to kind of view
37 really quick because it was a fun
discussion that we had
it also really sets the stage for how is
that similar or different than other
action perception partitionings or
models does evolutionary psychology or
evolutionary cognitive studies do they
have
a fundamental action perception model
at the root
is that a good thing is it a bad thing
section three goes into section two
again was just about how this single
slide and represented in figure one
about this predictive
so anticipatory but also embedded etc
infinity loop
cycle
is the basic principle of the brain we
can't take the basic principle of the
brain to be um some lower level like
just information transmission amongst
cells
nor do the authors jump in at a higher
level like the fundamental unit of
cognition is linguistic tokens that are
being modified not discrepancies with
multiple different kinds of things that
are being predicted
from this functional description of
cognition
they move to section three formulas
formalizing brain design as structured
learning in generative models
so what is the structure of this model
and then what does it look like to do
structure learning
in that model
and why is it generative
and then how is that formalized
so
here's figure two the generative model
and the generative process so the first
words the same second words different so
they're different words
and the figure on the left side has the
entity the figure on the right side has
the world state so it's the same action
perception loop we saw in figure one and
now this sort of conceptual flow
single edge model like just only one
arrow here no extra anything just sort
of
first pass
it's compatible with this which is
actually a bayesian graph but how do
they describe it and what are all the
variables
we still have the same things happening
we have the observations coming in to
the cognizing entity that's the
observations coming in
the entity is going to infer some action
policy
based upon the observations coming in
which is going to result in some change
to the actual underlying system which is
the generative process so that's like
the actual
birds and the beasts and the sun and
stuff
allegedly
it does get into a little bit of a gray
area with the realism instrumentalism
and the structural realism but we're not
even gonna go there in this discussion
right now the generative process is the
one that's handing out the observations
as modeled
the generative model to close the loop
is the entity's inference
and so here is x the entity's prediction
on hidden state and then here is x star
which is like the actual hidden state
that is being alleged in the world
and we've had some other discussions
about how that's the sigma function
that's like mapping between the two x's
that's what's being
minimized if the discrepancy is low
there's other notation
how do the authors describe it
the difference between the generative
model and the generative process
nodes correspond to probability
distributions and edges to their
statistical dependencies so this is like
a bayes graph
mathematically a generative model may be
formulated as the joint probability
density
p
of y and x of observations y and hidden
states x of the world that generate
those observations i think it was just a
copy error
the latter are referred to as hidden or
latent states as they cannot be observed
directly
the joint probability distribution can
be decomposed in two parts the first is
a prior p of x which denotes the
organism's knowledge about hidden states
of the world prior to seeing sensory
data
the second is the likelihood p of y
given x which denotes the organism's
knowledge of how observations are
generated from states so that's the
perceptual model
and then they go on to describe how
there's a difference between the
entity's inference on hidden state and
the actual hidden state which is the
generative process versus the generative
model distinction and then they
introduce action
and say action u that's this node that
influences the hidden state even if zero
effect
is generated based upon the inferences
made under a generative model
action is shown here as part of the
generative model
oh sorry
action is shown here as part of the
generative process
making changes to the world despite
being selected from the inference drawn
under the model so action is actually
making influence even again the edge
could be zero in some respect but it's
making actual influence in the world
it's like the active states interpreted
in this statistical way
so
what does that have to do um with
structure learning
so
the entity is going to either whether
you're realist and saying the entity is
doing structure learning or
you're instrumentalist
it is possible for us as researchers
today to model that entity as doing
structured learning because it's
computationally efficient or elucidative
or you go full utilitarian you just say
disregard that whole realism
instrumentalism it's a useful approach
and i'll follow utility wherever it goes
for any number of those reasons you
might want to model
the cognition of different entities
without going into just the philosophy
of what its cognitive process actually
is
and so one approach that's going to get
taken
is using
inference either from the outside
describing instrumentally or realism as
if it were happening maybe with
anatomical evidence
as if the hidden state could include not
just parameters that were continuous
about the world but also structures of
models
however it's difficult to imagine that
that type of cognitive or even extremely
metacognitive thought or action
selection
could happen for example in some early
however simple it may have been
and so how do we get from that flagella
changing bacterium
to
all the other kinds of cognition that we
see today
or should i say bacterium-like entity
relative or ancestor of today's bacteria
so how can we think about this model
which is often described in the context
of parameter learning and then approach
this as if it were
maybe about parameter learning sometimes
but also could be about structure in
terms of the good regulator and the
requisite diversity that kind of um
requisite variety those kinds of models
okay the next several sections are where
they get to the specifics and some of
the contributions of the paper that i
think will be really cool to
continue the discussion on
section four is just short and it's
saying we're about to go into three
examples of simple predictive motifs in
ancestral brains because one of the main
claims of the paper is that these motifs
are
very
ancestral they're old motifs they're not
johnny come lately to the cognitive
scene these are features that one can
think of as
who knows how far back or how simple
these cognitive mechanisms have existed
but we'll evaluate that maybe when we
get to talk together but first we'll
just kind of go through how they define
them and use them
the three predictive motifs are
homeostasis allostasis and simple
behavioral control so first five
generative models for the homeostatic
control of enteroceptive
variables they write
the generative models
shown in figure 3 which we'll look at
after this slide
afford the homeostatic
regulation of a single enteroceptive
variable
which we call here body temperature for
illustrative purposes
much like a thermostat this model
maintains the requisite body temperature
by reporting the discrepancy between
predicted and sensed thermoreceptor
activation given bayesian beliefs about
temperature triggering an autonomic
reflex u resulting in for example
vasodilation which resolves the
prediction error so if the life of the
organism were just to hang out on the
beach and vasodilate to off heat when it
needed to and then to constrict and to
save more heat when it needed to that's
the physiological task that this is
going to be describing
which is just one facet of an organism's
biology but there are experiments that
sometimes only measure temperature
and so thinking instrumentally
this single factor model
this single variable model on body
temperature may be sufficient for some
experiments or
it may be useful in certain cases so
just because it's a simple model doesn't
mean that it's not going to be very
educational
and provocative but also even be
sufficient in a lot of cases
but no one's even claiming it's realism
that's why it's written this way
they say see citation 20 for a fully
specified example and that is a citation
to
chance
at all in march 2022 so still in the
future
and they write we start from the
presence premise and this is in the
paper that again is from the future
we start from the premise that the goal
of enteroceptive control is to minimize
discrepancy between
expected and actual interroceptive
sensations i.e a prediction error
or free energy
importantly living organisms can achieve
this goal by using various forms of
enteroceptive control homeostatic
allostatic and gold directed
so
there's more details in this paper
but
here in figure 3 is where they're going
to show it so keep in mind this
generative model structure
and now
these are going to be
in a different form
and here in the caption i'll describe
what they say
this is that homeostatic the first most
ancestral or just the simplest possible
just
go make it darker if it's too bright and
make it brighter if it's too dark make
it warmer if it's too cold make it
colder if it's too warm that kind of
first order cybernetic loop
this generative model includes an
enteroceptive thermoreceptor y
observations and a belief about body
temperature x
so that's the beliefs about how the body
should be and that's again
the beliefs playing that dual function
that the paper 37 drew out
which is that
on the left side of this equation
failure to satisfy the preferences
is dealing with this p distribution as a
preference
but then on the right side p has to do
with expectations that are being either
fit well or poorly
and so this is where active inference
has a slightly different architecture
perhaps than some other theories
the beliefs are about body temperature
it's not an estimate merely of the
external body temperature
crucially the prior over x is kept fixed
and hence it acts as a cybernetic set
point
well you can't just expect what's going
to be best for you you'll die right if
you die you die
but if you enact
policy such that your expectations are
realized then you persist that's why
we're studying things that are persist
ant
any discrepancy between the predicted
thermoreceptor activity given beliefs
about x and the measured y is registered
as a prediction error that is canceled
out by an autonomic response for example
a thermoregulatory response
this is shown as an illustrative plot of
the expectations of prior and posterior
observation and autonomic actions over
time so here is like the action policy
which is like be at the baseline level
of thermoregulation and then kick in
some sweating or um cooling mechanism
and then here it describes how the
observations start at about 37.1 and
then they steadily start climbing
and then the belief which is initially
like things should be 37.
the posterior the after evidence
estimate starts creeping up and then it
hits a certain value and it engages a
critical threshold that turns on this
thermoregulatory response and then that
cools the temperature back down
so
this is a basic architecture for doing
first order cybernetics and that kind of
first order logic
here in this figure the red circles
represent the expected values of x which
are used to make predictions about y
these are subtracted
red arrow with the rounded end
so this one
from the measured y to form a prediction
error dark blue circle epsilon
which is used to update the expectation
and drive action light blue circle you
here's you
that changes y
such that the prediction error is
resolved
what if it doesn't do it well then the
system dies
so we're talking about evolution where
we've had like for the ants 120 million
years allegedly for that to get pruned
out and even longer at the cellular
level
note the lateral modulatory connections
in the allostatic network which we'll
get to in a second so just to take one
little discourse
they say c24 for details what is pape24
it is fristen par and devry's 2017 the
graphical brain belief propagation and
active inference
let's just look at a few parts of this
awesome paper
so first they have a table with
definitions of the technical terms
so just to kind of read a few but it's
kind of awesome to see the authors do
this and this isn't great paper as well
so how do they define generative model
generative model or forward model
a probabilistic mapping from causes to
observed consequences data
so from hyperparameter
to the parameter
it is usually specified in terms of the
likelihood of getting some data given
their causes parameters of a model and
priors on the parameters so it's all
relative in nested models but this is
generating data like kind of cranking
out like a music box
possible or plausible data sets with
similar summary statistics like similar
mean and variance
of some distribution or similar
parameters if there's a whole vector
that describe it and then the
recognition model
is related to learning where new data
are coming in and discrepancy is being
minimized if the generative is
outputting the exact same mean and
variance that incoming data are having
the discrepancy is low
the predictions which are about
preferences are being realized
successfully action policy is working
well or better than expected
flip everything and you have the
opposite situation
and then just to give one more
definition here because the next slide
will feature it though the others are
also good to read
factor graph
a factor graph is a bipartite graph
where two distinct sets of nodes are
connected by edges
representing the factorization of a
function usually a probability
distribution function
formulating a bayesian network or model
as a factor graph enables the efficient
computation of marginal distributions
through the sum product
algorithm
what does a factor graph look like and
how does it relate to the kinds of
bayesian graphs that we've been looking
at
so on the top is not the base graph
that's distributed across this slide but
another variant that we've seen a bunch
of times which is the partially
observable markov decision process so g
expected free energy minimization
pi policy selection is influencing b
which is how s the latent state in the
world is changing through time there's d
the prior on the hidden state and then a
the mapping of how the state is related
to the observation
and so depending on how the model is
framed those can be learned or not but
it turns out that because of how this is
relatively sparsely connected within a
time frame
as well as across time frames there's a
way to use this bipartite construction
called a factor graph that splits up
those unlabeled edges which are
statistical dependencies and kind of
interweaves
functions which have a slightly
different representation and it turns
out that by interleaving these functions
into the variables
it's possible to
make what's called a factor graph and
that gives an order of operations to
arbitrary or within a certain set
any kind of base graph but it includes
this one importantly and so here is the
one two three time points and two
policies are being selected and that's
what this graph represents the organism
comes in with the prior
time step one two three there's two
actions
and then
here's another figure from the paper
where at each of those three time steps
one two and three a little bigger
at time steps one two and three
there's the
inference happening on time steps one
two and three so time step one that's
like anticipation and planning at time
step two it's like short term
anticipation as well as memory and time
step three it's like memory and it's
always now casting as well and so one
can imagine that this is a really useful
format because it's extremely composable
on one hand so just like they said okay
well we kind of have this motif for the
three time steps and the connectedness
what if d
from the top level
came down and was s at a lower level and
we've seen that taken to a really
elaborated extent as well as interpreted
in for example the paper on mental
action in live stream 25.
and so factor graphs are awesome because
they're
basically needing to only be specified
in the bayes graph format
but then it provides not just a mesh
connectivity but a process algorithm
and a heuristic an approach that's
actually tractable so we get the
composable analytical and graphical
component that's an attractable
algorithm
the next section is generative models
for the allostatic control of
enteroceptive variables so this is going
to be the first real modification of the
homeostat that's introduced in three
this is going to be the base case but it
could be something else other than body
temperature
the homeostat is simple but limited as
they write it can counter sensed changes
of body temperature but cannot
anticipate predictable changes of body
temperature or other variables
in nature
there are several regularities eg night
day or seasonal alternation that can be
easily incorporated to extend the above
generative model as technically speaking
empirical priors the obvious advantage
of predicting how our bodily and
enteroceptive variables will change
is being able to exert some anticipatory
or allostatic control and so this is
kind of getting into the second order or
anticipatory cybernetics also related to
rosen's
anticipatory ecology
so here's figure 3 c
in
a and b there was just the homeostat
returning us to a set point after
something got triggered
and now there's going to be the
affordance for anticipatory control
this generative model
sketched out with the same scheme
as the previous
slide
this generative model extends the
homeostat by including a second set of
exterceptive variables
that correspond to light intensity white
y2
and a belief about sunrise x2
that's the sun visual side on the right
furthermore like the visual system
and the left side still the temperature
and terraceptive system furthermore the
model includes a predictive relationship
between sunrise x2
and body temperature y this edge isn't
saying that the sun warms the body it's
saying that they're in this model
there's an edge reflecting a statistical
dependency and that's where there's the
degree of freedom with respect to the
realism and instrumentalism etc
in this way inferring a sunrise can
trigger the autonomic response u of
thermoregulation in an anticipatory
manner that is before the sunlight
actually increases body temperature
the upper part of a and c are bayesian
networks highlighting that y is
conditionally dependent upon x with the
directed arrow between the notes with
more than one x and y in the model for
the allostat
the lower parts show the form of
neuronal message passing that could be
used to solve these generative models
so the bayes graph is represented on the
top and then there's the message passing
with respect to the neural population
so that's kind of the second
[Music]
aspect of figure 3 which is just
bringing in multi-sensory integration or
even it could be like two pixels for
example with beliefs about each other or
something like that but that's what
allostasis is going to be enabled by is
just by this duplication of the column
and then this connection in a different
way
and then here's the third section of
four seven
generative models for simple behavioral
control and so they write
the homeostat and the allostat permit
the control of simple forms of swimming
locomotion reaching and other movements
one biological example
is provided by the zebrafish virtual
reality study 30
which identified the neuronal
underpinnings of error correction during
escape behavior in the animal's
telecephalon to brain region an
evolutionary conserved set of brain
circuits involved in action selection in
other vertebrates including mammals such
as the corticobasal ganglia circuit
so that's about the evolutionary
homology of the brain region and then
here's just some pictures from the paper
um
by
torygo
at all21
zebrafish capable of generating future
state prediction error show improved
active avoidance behavior in virtual
reality so
they did a learning task that involved
the fish being able to differentiate a
signal and then they studied the role of
anticipation in that and the authors in
this paper
use that as an example
maybe we could talk about that or other
examples in
the dot one and the dot two
section eight
here's where we get to the um
very interesting
operations that are going to bring this
sort of descriptive model of different
kinds of homeostatic allostatic and
intermodal and then behavioral
regulatory elements into the
evolutionary context so
our central argument is that evolution
proceeded via gradual elaborations of
the predictive motifs illustrated above
under genetic constraints and
opportunities
and the selective pressure of novel
problems to be solved
such as the control of more
sophisticated bodies in the presence of
richer ecological niches eg when
vertebrates began to establish life on
land some 400 million years ago
over excessive generations
generative models can remain stable or
be elaborated along four key dimensions
strongly limiting the space of what is
evolvable
so what are the four kinds of dimensions
that are going to be changed
that is going to be
discussed in terms of the changes that
can happen to
the specifics of the generative model
we have introduced the first kind of
elaboration
from the unimodal homeostat to the
multimodal allostat so they kind of
secretly introduced this transformation
between figure 3ab and figure 3c
so that was secretly like one of the
transformations
a second kind of elaboration is the
duplication of predictive motifs which
enlarges the animal's behavioral
repertoire
the third and fourth dimensions equip
the generative model with temporal and
or hierarchical depth respectively
these two expansions enable richer
predictive motifs that endow a cognitive
sophistication
such as the possibility to plan or
consider events that change on multiple
time scales
so it's the evolutionary algebra
on structure learning
because we're outputting a structure
this graph g
which is going to be like
as if the species over evolutionary time
is going to be implementing some graph
in terms of the structure of its model
like
if there's a case where the ant is not
integrating the polarization of light
with the olfactory system
and then there's some change in the
model that actually integrates them and
then some relationship is learned
whatever that means from a realist or
instrumentalist perspective
and that is going to be like an
evolutionary algebra so it's not going
to be like
2x minus 3x but it's going to be more
like that than not because there's going
to be operations and they're going to
happen in order
so here's figure 4 where they represent
their evolutionary algebra figure four
the five main dimensions of elaboration
of generative models introduced in the
paper
so it was you know
four dimensions then it's five
dimensions there's evolution in 4d
by jablonka and lamb
that would have been good to add to
um
the five main dimensions of elaboration
of generative models introduced in the
paper illustrated as operations of an
evolutionary algebra so here's the five
operations and so we're starting with on
the left side that homeostat that simple
corrective calibrative first order
cybernetic model
either what the system is actually doing
or model of
then there's going to be five
transformations that can happen and then
it's showing there's a second round like
once you go h you could go h t a
i plus i or i
so you have five discrete options at the
first time step but one of them is no
change so it's kind of like no change or
four different layers of um excitement
of the electron like for quanta but
they're for discrete operations like a
deletion or an insertion in genomics and
then from there it's just the state for
the next time step of the model and then
something else happens so what are the
operations
the bottom is i which is the identity
operation that leaves the generative
model as is
so that can be interpreted as like a
non-mutation or just a conservative mode
which is how most inheritance works
then the second one is the duplication
operation i plus i so it's like identity
remains the same but then there's a
duplication literally it's like a
genomic duplication
but
in this functional space
replicates existing predictive motifs to
form parallel sensory motor loops
a is the operation that was described in
figure 3c the allostatic operation
endows the generative model with
horizontal predictive relations between
different modalities and so the
duplication would be like going from one
sensilla one antenna to two antenna or
from going from one photoreceptor to two
photoreceptors but the actual
architecture of the column
of the photosensory transduction cascade
would basically be computationally
or statistically unchanged and then the
allostat is actually bringing in this
horizontal aspect it's not just two um
duplicated systems next to each other
now there's actually connections between
them and of the possible kinds of
connections across columns one of them
is like this classic allostatic motif
then there's the ones that we haven't
gone into as much which are t
the temporal depth operation extends the
generative model with separate variables
for past present and future states
so it's kind of from a graphical
perspective what we looked at in the
difference between
the first factor graph
which did take action at three time
steps through time three time steps
like the thermostat does to the one that
actually has either prospectively
looking anticipation about future time
steps or retrospectively looking memory
but that's how the factor graph comes
into play
that's temporal depth
then
the hierarchical depth operation h
extends the generative model with
separate variables for states of affairs
that change at different time scales
faster time scales at the bottom levels
and slower time scales at the higher
levels hence modeling narratives such as
music and language where nested time
skills are relevant
so to kind of split that idea of
temporal depth into two pieces there's
incrementing the number of steps you're
looking in the model that's increasing
the time horizon on policy selection and
increasing the temporal depth within a
level and then there's this notion of
nesting
levels within each other that's the
nested generative model
and therefore nested markov blanket
discussion that we've been having
and that
is going to be connected to
cognitive activities like narrative and
the the reason why they're very similar
is that the time scales can kind of blur
into each other and so it's all about
the model's structure as stated
like this one is hierarchical
and it has a depth of three it's a two
layer model and it has a depth of three
three time steps are included
and it could be different if there was
always looking to a head and always
looking to in the back then the model in
the computer would need like a minimum
of you know five time steps but the
entities model could still be restricted
to s minus 2 s minus 1 and then s plus 1
s plus 2.
so
um
those are the two ways that it can
expand in these two temporal and
hierarchical ways which is to nest
hierarchically or to become temporally
deeper with a longer horizon given the
nesting structure so these are all
structural changes that's why there was
the whole piece about structure learning
because it's as if or actually like over
evolutionary time there's the structure
learning happen and then if we use this
partitioning and bayes graph approach
then
hypothetically any kind of evolutionary
starting point if we go back far enough
and then
final state if we have all the
transitions could be modeled within like
a native active inference framework
section nine they're going to go into a
little more detail about duplicating
predictive motifs and enabling multiple
behaviors
so they write
how does this um the writing on how does
this duplication of the model
um looking at it from the outside it's
like as if they're acting as if there's
two models looking at it from the
realism and the inside it's kind of like
thinking about the real duplication of a
cognitive function that's functionalism
or like even a neuroanatomical region
like the earlier examples with the
retinal cells and that's like an
anatomical realism
so generative models can expand by
duplicating simple predictive motifs to
form a larger repertoire of
species-specific behaviors such as
approach avoidance
the control of the vibrasay
and visually guided grasping classic
the operator i plus i in figure 4
illustrates a generative model in which
the same predictive motifs are
duplicated and specialized to form a
behavior-based architecture composed of
multiple parallel sensory motor loops so
they're suggesting that because these
are your affordances your operations in
your evolutionary algebra you can go
from this starting point it's kind of
like go to lesser block starting point
and then doing operations to it because
you have the starting point and the
operations to it it allows you to get to
even relatively advanced um
motifs like approach avoidance etc
but a key piece is duplication because
duplication of something without
changing it is how you are able to
build more land to experiment in so to
speak build more space and um
i copied some images from genetics
specifically in the relationship of how
gene duplication and divergence in the
early evolution of vertebrates this
paper
um and there's a huge amount of genetics
and genomics works on the duplication
and divergence and the
neo-functionalization the
sub-functionalization
because if you have like an enzyme or a
essential gene a
not to go into the whole gene thing
totally another time though
um
you could have the function of the
second copy in the genome be lost and
then there is still like a continuous
line of function so if you only needed
one copy of a
then this would be sufficient and then
other times when you have a and it's
dual functional like it binds to two
different not exactly similar molecules
then when there's a paralogy when
there's this duplication it allows sub
functionalization or new functions to
arise so that's how people talk about it
and link it to realism in genomics and
this is kind of approaching that from a
cognitive perspective
um there's probably more to say but
we'll talk more about the duplicating of
predictive motifs so how is duplicating
predictive motifs
enabling of multiple behaviors
okay they write from a structure
learning perspective duplication is an
efficient way of building generative
models and that's what it's all about in
the sense that the dynamics are
conserved over different sensory motor
domains
this conservation is mathematically
akin to factorizing probability
distributions on the generative model
that has been discussed in terms of
modular architectures and functional
segregation as a principle of functional
brain architectures
in bayesian statistics physics this kind
of factorization is ubiquitous and known
as a mean field approximation
indeed the free energy bound on model
evidence is defined in terms of a mean
field approximation
that affords an accurate and minimally
complex explanation for sensory data
and so what are some of these citations
modular architectures for factorization
of probability distributions in the
generative model
par sageed and firsten 2020 entropy
so here's kind of a cool figure
nice graph
and then there's the message passing
and then
citation 48 the mean field approximation
what is it
here's a paper from 2001
and they wrote algorithms that must deal
with complicated global functions of
many variables often exploit the manner
in which the given functions factor as a
product of local interactions each of
which depends on a subset of the
variables
such a factorization can be visualized
with a bipartite graph
that we call a factor graph
dot dot a wide variety of algorithms
developed in artificial intelligence
signal processing
and digital communications can be
derived as specific instances of the sum
product algorithm
including the forward backward algorithm
the viterbi algorithm the iterative
turbo decoding algorithm pearl's 1988
belief propagation algorithm for
bayesian networks
markov blankets
the common filter and certain fast
fourier transforms fft algorithms
so
it was 21 years ago when this was
happening and now we're here
okay section 10 endowing generative
models with temporal depth supports
prospective and retrospective inference
so
just like we looked at with that factor
graph
giving this operation
over evolutionary time enables that
factor graph to arise from something
with the lower time horizon
the generative models discussed so far
only consider present states and
observations however they can be
expanded into temporally deep models
whose variables explicitly represent
future and past states and observations
so this is what the operation looks like
it takes x t and then at x
t plus one or tau depending on how it's
written and then now there's another
time step appended to the end of this
model either actually or as if
here's something cool that they wrote
they wrote various researchers have
speculated that a major driving force
for the development of deep temporal
models was foraging so why would this
happen functionally which is to say
why does the mutational spectra
which does allow for this as an
affordance end up selecting for and
retaining and enriching for temporally
deep models otherwise we wouldn't
observe it to exist
and they're connecting that to foraging
intriguingly this is a vertebrate
example
the same hippocampal circuits that
support spatial navigation and foraging
are also involved in prospection and
imagination
this has led busaki and mosser to
propose that prospective functions have
leveraged cognitive and predictive maps
in the hippocampal endorinal system and
hence mechanisms of memory and planning
have evolved from mechanisms of
navigation in the physical world
so what are the cognitive demands of
foraging
how about information foraging how about
mental foraging
here's some awesome papers by hills and
cuisine and others
foraging in mind
and foraging in semantic fields how we
search through memory so what about
mental foraging
what about individual and collective
foraging
this is an awesome paper by finerman and
corman in 2017
and they talk about the continuum and
the complementarity of individual and
collective approaches to cognition and
so implicitly like foraging as a
phenomena
some of the affordances and the
neurophysiology of foraging in ants it's
the same materials and mechanism that
any other insect that's not eusocial has
so the detection of light the intensity
the wavelength polarization sometimes
the ability to do
chemo sensation like taste and smell
mechanoreception etc and the same action
affordances too like movement and so
there definitely is nest mate level
cognition in ants
but also there's things that are of a
few different interesting types one of
them is
mesoscale like small group dynamic
stochastic teams and larger scale like
colony and even colony niche stigma g
and ecological scale cognitive processes
like these two ants are interacting and
modifying each other's foraging behavior
mechanistically and statistically but
also it wouldn't happen unless the niche
were exactly this way which they have
also in their extended selves
established for themselves so
how do we think about individual and
collective foraging
and stigma g and complex systems
and mental foraging and cognitive
demands and cognitive security
what about section 11 endowing
generative models with hierarchical
depth affords multi-scale inference so
now we get to the hierarchical operation
that is going to give that multi-scale
inference
so far we have described generative
models that can deal with aspects of the
world that unfold at single time scale
so plus one plus one plus one time scale
is temporal depth but you're getting
still only one extra per transformation
however they can be expanded into
hierarchically deep models
whose variables at different
hierarchical levels encode latent states
that unfold at different time scales one
example is a song melody remains the
same even though the notes we hear or
sing change rapidly and speech
similarly a movie or narrative remains
the same for several minutes scenes
remain the same for several seconds but
visual stimuli can change over hundreds
of milliseconds
such models permit hierarchical models
permit
modeling of narratives
songs
movies and other events that change at
different temporal scales by encoding
variables that change more slowly eg
melodies or movies at higher
hierarchical levels
and variables that change more rapidly
eg notes or visual scenes at lower
hierarchical levels
two neurobiological examples of
hierarchical organization are visual
areas in mammals and areas that control
vocal gestures in birdsong
which has been studied in active
inference several times
and so here's another quote from the
authors
in more advanced animals the
hierarchical control of action may have
expanded into sophisticated forms of
cognitive control and executive function
layer 1 scare quotes
which help prioritize distal goals while
inhibiting immediate affordances
so
it's not just about seeing deeper within
a time scale
but it's about being able to pull up to
a higher time scale and then from there
after the h operation
it can be followed up with a t operation
so here's the minute scale
and then there's a hierarchical
duplication that allows for the hour
scale
and then that can go into two hours and
now two minutes so now there's a two
hour and two minute
long model instead of a one minute and
it was just two mutations but if the two
mutations had been um
or the three mutations had been just
going deeper within the minutes
it would be a different outcome
how is that um functional so what is the
function and the cost of temporal depth
just instrumentally
when we're studying diverse cognitive
systems how can we detect temporal depth
and slash versus hierarchical nesting
then what is the meaning and the role of
narrative in cognition how does this
relate to
narrative information management
all right section 12 getting towards the
end
in the above which was again the
description of the simple motifs in four
five six seven
and then the evolutionary algebra in
eight and then several of these finer
scale discussions on 9 and 10
and 11
we then get to 12.
in the above we formalize brain designs
in terms of generative models that
include predictive loops of various
complexity
red
and then discuss the five main ways in
which generative model designs can be
elaborated green
or the five main operations of an
algebra of evolutionary structure
learning figure four
this means that one can describe the
evolutionary trajectory of brain designs
in terms of a limited number of
mutational operations over generative
models blue
so
here is a phylogenetic tree on the right
side with the
tree of life one of the tree of lives
what are alternative complementary or
traditional ways to think about
phylogenetic trees
in evolutionary biology
are phylogenetic trees interpreted
instrumentally
are they interpreted under a realism
framework is that what really happened
to those species or is it our model
inference about
what is the relationship between active
inference and the free energy principle
and
evolution
okay
they have figure 5 which gets at their
phylogenetic model so this is a
phylogenetic tree of generative model
designs
and putative correspondences with animal
brains so here's the implied ancestral
state and then
i
is going to be the identity operator so
here the orange species has not mutated
at all
now
sometimes this is um conflated with
simply being an out group it just
because it is that way doesn't mean
they're making the conflation but
sometimes people will make the
conflation that because a species is an
out group to some other clade
that has been included in the analysis
that it is the basal or primitive form
and so it does happen to be that way in
this example that the basal is the
so-called least derived or most
primitive or basal form but
my personal
thought is that it should not be
described and
tim link's fair and others have awesome
writing on that evolutionary fallacy
so in the rest of the tree which is
being focused on
different kinds of operations happen so
here's that i plus i duplication and
then
there's no change after that and then
this one has a and so on so
just like you could trace the phenotype
changing through time on a tree inferred
from
trait or genomic data which is just
another trait
this maps up to certain changes that are
seen neuroanatomically over vertebrate
evolution
and it reminded me of this paper which
was um
chakraborty and jarvis 2015
and so that is the paper brain evolution
by brain pathway duplication so they
don't connect it to um in the exact same
way the neural cognitive and the
functional and the active inference and
all that but this paper does get out
some of the very similar ideas about the
functional duplication arising as a
result of
pathway duplication
they have
a section on brain complexity and
pathway evolution they talk about some
alternative hypotheses and then talk
about distributed and duplicated
morphological structures so it's a kind
of interesting paper from about seven
years ago
another paper that's very related to
this idea of doing like an evolutionary
algebra with combinatorics but also a
path dependence is this paper
pretty recently just a couple days ago
by ryan smith maxwell ramstead and alex
kiefer the paper is why bayesian brains
perform poorly on explicit probabilistic
reasoning problems
so look at this tree that they have the
starting point and then three actions so
here it's like divide divide multiply
divide
add divide
and then they study that in the context
of bayesian brains and doing
calculations why is it hard to multiply
numbers together sometimes
so then the authors of the paper 38
right interestingly the mutational
operators are commutive the same
generative model design can be obtained
by executing the same operations but in
a different order
the commutative property of mutational
operators potentially sheds light on the
convergent evolution
and the process by which unrelated
organisms evolve similar traits
independently
and via different evolutionary histories
when they need to adapt to similar
ecological niches
that's pretty cool
all right so just the discussion and
then a few last points so discussion and
the authors summarize it in this article
we suggest that brain structure or
design could be formalized as generative
models agree disagree
that the brain generative models of our
evolutionary ancestors included simple
predictive motifs
agree disagree
and that the evolution proceeded via
successive elaborations of these
predictive motifs into more complex
architectures that we observe in
advanced animals they then talked about
the ways that that can change through
time functionally
and then they write
while the evolutionary trajectory of
designs for predictive processing
proposed here is certainly tentative and
incomplete we consider it a first step
towards the alignment of predictive
brains and evolutionary studies of
neuroanatomy in different species
so if this is the first step where are
we headed and why do we prefer and
expect ourselves to be there or go there
just a few more topics that we could
talk about like in the dot one and in
the dot two
um first would be
they write that the error correction
mechanisms
in their view encompass the simple
and the complex forms of adaptive
behavior
hashtag integrative theory
and they're going to argue that that
differs significantly from prevalent
perspectives in psychology and
neuroscience
which tend to separate sets of mechanism
for sensory motor processing and simple
cognition
so how is active inference similar and
different to other frameworks for
behavior
what are the building blocks of adaptive
what are the basal blocks of just any
kind of behavior
where does sensory motor integration
come into play
how about mental functions and cognitive
functions
like memory anticipation counterfactuals
etc
okay another point to kind of think
about or write your questions down and
reflect on
is the perspective which is still
speculative and not unchallenged
suggests that the complexity of the
ecological niche determines the level of
complexity that the brain needs to have
in order to be bayes optimal
in other words brains only increase
their complexity with sufficient
ecological demands
so not necessarily just that mutational
direction and intensity will
go towards increasing brain complexity
from ecological demands the so-called
anticipatory evolution that cognitive
entities can have through
self-modification and niche modification
but even for those that aren't actually
doing anticipation still it could be the
case that when the ecological demands
are such that a behavioral model
increase in complexity is selected for
and retained then evolution will go that
way
this is because having a more
complicated brain does not help if you
live in a simple niche so that's like a
very costly model that's not giving you
any more return on investment
they then talk about how social brain
hypothesis states that the necessity to
predict and deal with sophisticated
social dynamics was a main driver of the
evolution of large brains and
sophisticated cognitive abilities in our
species people
in short the gradualism
expressed as a progressive increase in
complexity rests on the circular
causality implicit in the modeling of an
echo niche that is itself constituted
and constructed by increasingly
complicated phenotypes so
because it's so important to think
through other minds first just how
you're going to materially avoid a
spatial collision but then so the social
brain hypothesis goes includes
increasingly recursive levels of game
theory market theory and all this kind
of stuff and related indirect cognitive
phenotypes required like memory and
recognition
narrative understanding rhetorical
understanding governance etc
that is being
posited as compatible with the models
the authors have written and a
hypothesis that others have written
about not from an active inference
perspective though in most cases so what
is the cognitive niche for social
entities our material niche and our
social cognitive niche
what is the social brain
what is the you social brain
how are they related
so for example the social brain
is saying that the more social things
are the more sophisticated the brain has
to be well you need more narrative
understanding and more memory
but what if in the eu social case the
brain is simpler on board for example
it's more role-based or temporal
polyethylism has allowed more reduction
in the
each phase of the life cycle's brain so
does social lead to you social
how does your sociality arise and how
does it elaborate
how do different kinds of sociality
arise and elaborate and how is that
associated with the different kinds of
models
structurally changing that we've been
discussing in this paper and then just
genomics all the other stuff gene
expression
and then just one last point
which is the closing piece of their
paper too
finally it is important to acknowledge
that brains design bodies
ecological and cultural niches
co-evolved independently
not sure if that was dement it's kind of
like they are codependent in their
co-evolution but they co-evolved
they were alone together
given that here we were interested in
the evolution of brain designs we
assumed a brain-centric perspective and
conveniently focused on generative
models in the animal's brain
hashtag realism
in the brain not modeled as in the brain
however cognition does not need to be
confined in the skull to be
it can be extended outside it to cover
for example tools and social dimensions
epistemic niche niche modification
digital stigma she furthermore the body
design and not just brain design plays
an important role in solving control
problems acknowledging that cognition
can be extended and embodied and in
cultured etc all the e's all the other
letters
suggests that not all aspects of control
need to be solved by or represented in a
central generative model
tale of two densities
all the discussions we've been having
about representation and so it was x and
x star in the simple version that was
presented in this paper where was
actually trying to track x star in the
world with the internal inference but
this is the discussion that we've been
having
do those representations have to
structurally resemble
the world and there's other papers that
we've discussed in the last several
weeks that really touch on that point so
how do we think about generative models
and factor graphs
for extended cognitive processes
so a couple books to check out about
extended mind and embodied cognition and
then here's a nice figure from touch
points
with
the brain
the organs and the body
the world and the tools and the
epistemic niche and the computers like a
calculator and time chronos
and food and then other people
social so that's like cognition is like
a holistic integration of all these
features
what does embodiment
this perspective have to do with realism
and instrumentalism
and utilitarianism and other
philosophical positions
are people really taking those positions
or is it just as if they're taking those
positions
and then what else are you really
curious about and motivated to explore
and how will you modify and improve your
epistemic niche
so
hope you enjoyed this kind of
solo
0 video i think it's been a little bit
since the solo.0s
but just want to close as always with
what might a good understanding enable
what are the unique predictions and
implications
what are the next steps for free energy
principle and active inference research
and application
what are the goals of this research
and what are you
still curious about
we're going to be talking about this
paper
in the coming weeks
on february 16th and february 23rd
and so if you'd like to participate in
those
discussions through live chat or by
joining the discussions live just get in
contact with us hope you read this paper
because it's very thought provocative
and uh interesting so
enjoy the paper and
working through it i hope to see you in
other acting flap activities
thanks for listening in your regime of
attention goodbye